Guide to the Phyllis McClure Civil Rights in Education collection, 1969-2010 MS2313
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Phyllis McClure Civil Rights in Education collection
1957-2010
1969-2010
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
McClure, Phyllis
Brown, Cynthia G.
MS2313
2 Linear Feet 4 document boxes
Phyllis McClure (1938-2010) was a longtime civil rights activist and advocate for disadvantaged students in U.S. public schools. In her position at the NAACP Legal Defense and Education Fund from 1969 through 1994, she was known for exposing the misuse of federal money under the Title I program of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965. She demonstrated that school districts were regularly using Title I funds, which were intended to improve education for impoverished students, for their own general expenses. Later in her career she was an advocate for the 2002 No Child Left Behind law. This collection contains her rticles, reports, clippings, newsletters, and other publications, as well as correspondence, notes, and tapes and transcripts of oral histories. It dates from 1969 to 2010.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Articles and reports; and Subject files
Biographical / Historical
Phyllis McClure (1938-2010) was a longtime civil rights activist and advocate for disadvantaged students in U.S. public schools. In her position at the NAACP Legal Defense and Education Fund from 1969 through 1994, she was known for exposing the misuse of federal money under the Title I program of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965. She demonstrated that school districts were regularly using Title I funds, which were intended to improve education for impoverished students, for their own general expenses. Later in her career she was an advocate for the 2002 No Child Left Behind law.
McClure graduated from the University of Connecticut in 1960, received a master's degree in history from the University of California at Berkeley, served in the Peace Corps in Nigeria, and received a master's in public administration from the Kennedy School of Government at Harvard. She began her career working on federal desegregation efforts in the civil rights office of the Office of Education in 1964, and joined the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights in 1966.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Other Finding Aids
For related materials, please see also:
Cynthia Brown Office for Civil Rights Collection
William L. Taylor papers
Scope and Contents
This collection contains articles, reports, clippings, newsletters, and other publications, as well as correspondence, notes, and tapes and transcripts of oral histories. The material documents McClure's work studying the implementation of Title I programs for disadvantaged children, often exposing the misuse of funds and arguing for better opportunities for poor and minority children. It dates from 1969 to 2010.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cynthia G. Brown, 2012 (2012.084)
Educational change; Poverty; Brown, Cynthia G.
- Articles and reports, 1957-2009; Series 1; 1.5 Linear Feet 3 document boxes
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains articles, reports, clippings, newsletters, and other publications written by McClure from 1957 to 2009. It begins with newspaper clippings of her articles as an undergraduate at the University of Connecticut, and includes both draft and final reports on Title I, Title IV, Title IX, Chapter 1, and No Child Left Behind, as well as prepared remarks given by McClure and her 2009 volume Jeanes Teachers: A View into Black Education in the Jim Crow South.
  - Clippings -- Connecticut Daily Campus, 1957; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings -- Title I, 1969-1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1992-1994; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1994-1999; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Analysis of Title I in the Providence School Department, 2000; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Behind the Numbers: The Overrepresentation of Minorities in Special Education, 1994; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Book reviews, 1997; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chapter 1 Independent Review Panel, 1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chapter 1 and Title I: Major Differences at a Glance, 1994; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Days of Reckoning, 2006; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Deregulation of Title I: A Lesson to be Learned from the Past, 1982; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Effect of Welfare Reform on Title I and Title I Schools, 1996; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ensuring Equal Opportunity in Public Education, 2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Erosion of Civil Rights Enforcement, 1986; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - From Title I to No Child Left Behind: The Past in the Present, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - High Standards for all Children, but Not in All Subjects, 1995; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Jeanes Teachers, 2009; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Journal articles on Title I, 1981-1992; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Law journal articles on education and civil rights, 1965-1993; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Let them Eat Reports, 1983; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Making Title I Work for Poor Children in the St. Louis Public Schools, 1996; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - McClure articles, 1994-1998; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minorities and Education in the Reagan Years, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mississippi's Future, 1988; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - NCLB: An Advocate's Dream, A Community's Challenge, 2002; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The National Assessment of Chapter 1, 1991-1992; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - National Evaluations: What Do They Mean to Local Title I Educators?, 1998; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The New Title I Compensatory Education Program: An Analysis, 1995; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - A New Tool for Middle School Reform, 1994; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - No Child Left Behind: A Description of State Responsibilities, 2002; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - The Politics of Federalism in Title I, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Portability Sounds Attractive, but Won't Work, 1999; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Public Schools: The Solution to Mississippi's Woes, 1997; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Racial Isolation in the Public Schools, 1967; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Reauthorizing the Vocational Education Act to Serve Black Americans, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Remarks on the twentieth anniversary of Title I, 1985; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Reply to New York Times article on vouchers, 2001; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Responses to McClure on Title I abuses, 1969-1972; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - School Improvement Under No Child Left Behind, 2005; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Schoolwide Programs: Implementing the Law, 1994-1995; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Speech to administrators on new Title I, 1994-1995; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - State Policies to Support Middle School Reform, 1998; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Statement before the Congressional Black Caucus on government lawlessness, 1972; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Title I 20th anniversary, 1985; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Title I in Alabama: The Struggle to Meet Basic Needs, 1999; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Title I of ESEA: Is it Helping Poor Children?, 1969; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Title I in Midstream, 1999; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Title VI and Title IX Compliance in State-Operated Special Purpose and Vocational Schools, 1976; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Waiver Requests Seek "Business as Usual" Rather than Fundamental Reform, 1995; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Where Do Your Federal Dollars Go?, 1998; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Where Standards Come From, 2005; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Subject files, 1961-2010; Series 2; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  This series contains correspondence, memos, resumes, statements, tapes, and transcripts primarily relating to Title I implementation and reform. The material dates from 1961-2010.
  - Alabama Title I, 1992-2006; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Carter, Judge Robert, 2002-2004; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Comparability of services in ESEA Title I schools, 1973-1975; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Comparability in Title I, 2008; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and memos, 1970-1973; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1970-1978; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - ESEA Title I, 1968; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Franklin, John Hope, 1961-1965; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - McClure memorial service, 2010; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - McClure resumes, undated; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Providence, RI, 2000; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Statements on testing, 1997; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Tapes and transcripts from McClure oral history, 2010; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Testing issues in Chapter 1, 1991; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Title I data/allocations, 1965-2005; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Title I history, 1986-1993; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Washington D.C. Title I allocations, 2007-2008; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 15)